FARRAH FATIDEH IT SECURITY RISK ANALYST

ffatideh@valencia.global



Farrah has 13 years' public and private sector experience, including 9 years experience providing expert advice on Global Governance, Compliance and Risk Management to top International and Canadian Federally Regulated Financial Institutions.

She held wide range of positions in international banks from 2010 to 2020. In 2019 she was assigned to lead an AML/Compliance team in reconstructing a more effective and risk-based AML/Compliance program at Alterna Savings/Bank. Her assignment began by building & training the required staff and resources to develop policy and progress keeping international and Canadian laws related to AML/ATF/Compliance, Risk Management and Privacy Risk.

Some of the latest challenges for her included managing projects related to third-party system updates to optimize daily, weekly and monthly reporting for the bank. She worked closely with the Executive Leadership Team and recommended measures and controls to manage operational risk. At J.P. Morgan Chase Farrah managed the Quality Control of reports and at HSBC and Alterna Savings she managed external audit & controlled and FINTRAC's examination.

Expertise: Leadership and soft skills, Regulatory Risk Management, strategy, Global Compliance and Governance. Managing and directing workforce with full accountability to align organization's structure with its strategic direction.

EDUCATION AND & CERTIFICATIONS

- 2007: Bachelor of Social Sciences (Criminology & Politics), University of Ottawa.
- In Progress: Lean Six Sigma, Green Belt, ASQ, Ottawa, ON
- 2020: Lean Six Sigma, White Belt, ASQ, Ottawa, ON
- 2019: Statistical Analysis System (SAS), SimpliLearn
- 2014: Suspicious Activity Report Training Program for U.S. Investigative Units,
- 2014: Anti-Corruption Compliance
- 2014: Global Sanction Compliance

OTHER ACTIVITIES, INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES

- **2017:** Swiss Finance Institute's Annual meeting Future Financing & Banking, Zurich Switzerland
- 2017: ACAMS conference Block Chain, Bitcoin Currency and Human Trafficking, Toronto ON
- 2016: Project Management Program Training, Whidbey, ON.

EXPERIENCE

- 4 years at the Government of Canada Federal and Provincial including Department of Fisheries and Ocean (Canadian Coast Guard – Icebreakers), Industry Canada (Spectrum Management), Transport Canada (Railway and Environmental Policy)
- Assistant to Director Generals, member of senior executive team

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

August 2020 to present, Consultant, IT Security Risk Analyst,

 Managing multiple projects related to IT, Cybersecurity and Enterprise Risk Management with Valencia team.

July 2016 – March 2020, Consultant, President, Alborz Business Management Inc. (Alterna Savings, Team Lead)

- Federally incorporated and independent Consultant offered assessment of AML/ATF and Compliance Program for Federally Regulated Financial Institutions.
- Led AML teams in reconstructing a stronger AML/Compliance program, utilized the existing AML IT system and program to maximize outcome with collaboration of third-party vendors and service providers.
- Assessed company's existing AML Program and formulated corrective actions and led the team in reconstruct a more effective risk-based program while ensuring the company meets its regulatory obligations.
- Realized potential gaps, challenges and risks, having enterprise and department's objective in mind, and recommended operational risk management process and service improvements (using Lean, Six Sigma methodologies).
- Created an action plan to correct the nonconformities identified during the external audit and examination followed by policy adjustments and risk assessment.
- Recommended measures and controls to manage operational risk in a more efficient manner, such as creation of processes for first and second line of defense.

- In addition to service improvement, formulated preventive actions to avoid the same nonconformity from occurring again.
- Took pre-emptive actions, such as departmental wide cross trainings, and allocated resources to complete regulatory reports (OSFI, FSRA, etc.).
- Provided consultative advice and guidance to build project capacity to make effective use of change management strategies and supported the team in integrating change management activities into project plan.
- Ensured quick corrective action of any identified issues related to privacy risk, security, AML and Compliance program, risk management, system update and procedures.
- Reviewed and developed related policies and risk assessment including training programs and recommend actions plans and guidance for improvements.
- Provided direction, interpretation, and guidelines concerning the existing Operational Policies.
- Directed the AML/Compliance team to create new processes and their implementation, following regulatory changes.
- Encouraged and promoted team-work environment that strive for collaboration and continuous improvement.
- Provided direct support and coaching to all levels of managements and Executive Leadership Team.

November 2018 – April 2019, Navigant Consulting Company, Toronto, ON, Risk Analyst (Global Governance, Risk & Compliance)

- Acted as an independent consultant to manage organization's backlog related to AML.
- Managed investigation of major financial crime;
 Reviewed investigation and deliver the findings in a comprehensive report.
- Recommend corrective actions to the appropriate line of business
- Identified potential violation of regulatory requirements, internal policies and procedures or other risk to the organization.

February 2018 – August 2018, Royal Bank of Canada, Toronto, ON, Risk Analyst (Financial Intelligence Unit)

- Acted as an independent consultant, to conduct financial forensic investigation and relevant research to mitigate regulatory, financial, reputational and market risk for the client.
- Managed major financial crime and AML related investigations; analyzed investigation and delivered the findings in a comprehensive report.

July 2016 – February 2018, HSBC Canada, AML Manager – Financial Crime Compliance, Operation Risk Admin Specialist

- Acted as an independent consultant, to manage department backlog through forensic investigation.
- Recommended new corporate training program in partnership with Organizational Development.
- Conducted quality control of reports; re-engineered a more accurate narrative for FINTRAC filings.
- Identified process gaps, proactively presented new methods to management to improve compliance program through optimization, flexibility of resource sharing and process workflow.
- Managed operational risk controls in accordance with HSBC or regulatory standards and policies.
- Supervised and provided guidance related to regulatory risks and front-line defense.
- Managed internal audit.

November 2011 – March 2016, J.P. Morgan Chase, Ottawa, ON, AML Analyst

- Coordinated User Acceptance Testing (UAT) activities for AML Operation and assisted the final testing and troubleshooting issues from the UAT activity.
- Facilitated and implemented action plans to address performance and operational risk issues.
- Managed internal audit and assisted with external audits, executed with satisfactory results.
- Initiated new tools to improve analytical reporting and developed policy framework, tools, regulatory and provision of analysis.
- Worked closely with project designer to integrate changes into a system solution.
- Provided mentorship, ensuring that the company has the talent in place to meet its competency needs.
- Assisted in writing and revamping AML procedures.
- Led and coordinated charity fundraisings, in line with company's social responsibility.
- Managed AML records retention.
- Managed quality control of reports and assisted the integration of departmental policy and procedures.
- Managed daily and quarterly regulatory reports.
- Executed quality review of management report and ensured SLAs were met.

August 2010 – November 2011, J.P. Morgan Chase, Ottawa, ON, Trainer - Financial Advisor

- Developed and executed face-to-face classroom training in various business units as required.
- Reviewed training materials related to Customer Service/Financial Service Advisors and advised other LOB about ongoing and specific AML / ATF trainings.
- Provided leadership to the new hire, set priorities and ensured the quotas were met.